<Document>
# Surgery

Surgery is for injuries that field medicine cannot finish: [color=#ff7070][bold]internal bleeding[/bold][/color], fractures, organ trauma, embedded shrapnel, eschar, alien embryos, amputations, missing limbs, and prosthetic work.

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Read the surgery examine text first.[/bold][/color] It tells you the body part, access state, and next valid tool. If this guide and the examine text disagree, the examine text wins.

[bold]Color key:[/bold] [color=#98d982]ideal[/color], [color=#ffd166]accepted substitute[/color], [color=#ff7070]danger or hard rule[/color], [color=#7ac7ff]access requirement[/color], [color=#c77dff]rare/special tool[/color].

## Quick Rules

- [bold]Stabilize first:[/bold] stop active bleeding, replace blood, manage pain, and move the patient onto a surgery table when possible.
- [bold]Target the right region:[/bold] surgery is body-part specific. A chest operation will not fix a leg problem.
- [bold]Open access in order:[/bold] incision, clamp bleeders, retract. Head and chest work may also need bone access.
- [bold]Do not close early:[/bold] closing an incision while surgical bleeders are still exposed can turn them into internal bleeding.
- [bold]Field care is not surgery:[/bold] gauze, trauma kits, burn kits, and splints are useful, but they do not replace the surgical step unless the surgery examine accepts them.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMScalpel"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMHemostat"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMRetractor"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMCautery"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMSurgicalDrill"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMCircularSaw"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMBonesetter"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMBoneGel"/>
</Box>

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMTraumaKit10"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMBurnKit10"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMSurgicalLine"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMSynthGraft"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUFixOVein"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUOrganClampItem"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUBoneGraftItem"/>
</Box>

## Surgical Access

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Shallow access[/bold][/color] is the normal opening route:

1. [color=#98d982][bold]Scalpel[/bold][/color]: open the incision.
2. [color=#98d982][bold]Hemostat[/bold][/color]: clamp surgical bleeders.
3. [color=#98d982][bold]Retractor[/bold][/color]: retract the incision.

Shallow access is enough for most limb, hand, foot, groin, stump, suturing, shrapnel, eschar, and reachable internal bleeding work.

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Deep access[/bold][/color] is needed for most chest and head organ work:

1. Open the incision.
2. Clamp bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Use a [color=#98d982][bold]circular saw[/bold][/color] or [color=#ffd166][bold]surgical drill[/bold][/color] to open bone access.

Compound or shattered fractures in the head or chest can provide bone access after the incision is opened and retracted. They do not let you operate through closed skin.

[bold]Closing up:[/bold]

1. Finish every exposed repair.
2. If bone access is open, use [color=#98d982][bold]bone gel -> bone setter -> bone gel[/bold][/color].
3. Close the incision with [color=#98d982][bold]cautery[/bold][/color].

## Common Repairs

### Wound Suturing

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] no full incision route. Target the wounded body part and use [color=#98d982][bold]surgical line[/bold][/color].

Suturing closes treated brute wounds. It does not repair fractures, organs, missing limbs, or internal bleeding.

[color=#ffd166][bold]Accepted substitutes:[/bold][/color] Fix-o-vein is suboptimal. RMC cable coil is a poor substitute.

### Internal Bleeding

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] shallow access on the bleeding region. Chest and head internal bleeding can be repaired from shallow access when the bleed is reachable.

1. Open the incision.
2. Clamp surgical bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Repair the bleed with [color=#98d982][bold]Fix-o-vein[/bold][/color].
5. Close with cautery when nothing else is exposed.

[color=#ffd166][bold]Accepted substitutes:[/bold][/color] surgical line can replace Fix-o-vein only during the surgical repair step. RMC cable coil is a bad substitute.

[color=#ff7070][bold]Hard rule:[/bold][/color] surgical line, gauze, and trauma kits do not field-fix internal bleeding from outside the body. You still need surgical access.

### Broken Bones

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] shallow access on limbs and extremities. Chest and head need deep access unless a compound or shattered fracture already exposes bone access.

[bold]Hairline, simple, or compound fracture:[/bold]

1. Open incision.
2. Clamp bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Apply [color=#98d982][bold]bone gel[/bold][/color].
5. Set the bone with a [color=#98d982][bold]bone setter[/bold][/color].
6. Apply bone gel again.
7. Close.

[bold]Shattered fracture:[/bold]

1. Open incision.
2. Clamp bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Apply bone gel.
5. Set the bone.
6. Insert a [color=#98d982][bold]bone graft[/bold][/color].
7. Set the grafted bone.
8. Apply bone gel again.
9. Close.

Casts are post-operative support. Apply them after surgery to stop malunion while the limb finishes knitting.

### Organ Repair

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] deep access for chest and head organs.

[color=#98d982][bold]Trauma kit[/bold][/color] is the ideal organ repair tool when the exposed organ step calls for organ repair. [color=#ffd166][bold]Organ vessel clamp[/bold][/color] is a suboptimal tool for serious vessel work. Eye and brain procedures are head surgeries and require trained surgery skill.

Organ removal and transplant work follows the same access ladder: open, clamp, retract, open bone access if needed, free or repair the organ, then close bone access and close the incision.

[color=#ff7070][bold]Warning:[/bold][/color] do not remove heart, brain, lungs, kidneys, liver, or stomach unless the patient can survive it or immediately receive a replacement.

### Foreign Object Removal

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] surface shrapnel may be removable directly. Surgical shrapnel needs the proper surgical access first.

Use a [color=#98d982][bold]hemostat[/bold][/color] when possible. Scalpel-family extractors can remove reachable fragments, but they are worse. Close the incision if one was opened.

Embedded fragments can hurt the patient when they move and can cause more damage. Remove them before sending the patient back out.

### Eschar Removal

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] shallow access.

1. Open incision.
2. Clamp bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Debride the eschar with a [color=#98d982][bold]scalpel[/bold][/color].
5. Close.

[color=#ffd166][bold]Accepted substitutes:[/bold][/color] burn kits and synth grafts are suboptimal. Cautery works, but it is worse than a scalpel.

### Alien Embryo Removal

[color=#7ac7ff][bold]Access:[/bold][/color] deep torso access and trained surgery skill.

1. Open incision.
2. Clamp bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Open bone access.
5. Cut embryo roots with a scalpel.
6. Remove the embryo with a hemostat.
7. Close bone access.
8. Close the incision.

Move quickly. A bursting embryo can make surgery impossible.

## Limb Surgery

### Amputation

Amputation requires a valid limb or extremity target and the normal access route. If you begin the muscle cut and need to back out, [color=#98d982][bold]Fix-o-vein[/bold][/color] or [color=#ffd166][bold]surgical line[/bold][/color] can cancel the amputation route and return the limb to the retracted access state.

1. Open incision.
2. Clamp bleeders.
3. Retract.
4. Use a scalpel to sever muscle and prepare the cut.
5. Use a circular saw or drill to remove the limb.
6. Seal the stump or prepare for reattachment.

### Stump Sealing

A severed hand or foot leaves a stump on that extremity. A severed arm or leg leaves a stump on that limb. A lost head leaves a stump at the chest.

1. Target the stump region.
2. Open incision if needed.
3. Clamp bleeders.
4. Retract.
5. Seal the stump with cautery, hemostat, Fix-o-vein, or surgical line.
6. Finish the vessel seal if the examine text still asks for it.
7. Close.

Sealing the stump stops stump bleeding. It does not restore the missing limb.

### Reattaching Limbs

After the stump is sealed, target the missing region and use the matching detached limb as the surgical tool. Biological limbs restore biological function. Robotic limbs restore prosthetic function and visual prosthetic overlays.

Whole robotic arms and legs bring their robotic hand or foot with them. Robotic limbs do not use normal biological wounds, fractures, or internal bleeding.

### Removing Prosthetics

Use a [color=#98d982][bold]circular saw[/bold][/color] for ideal prosthetic removal. A [color=#ffd166][bold]surgical drill[/bold][/color] can substitute. Prosthetic brute frame damage is repaired with a lit welder. Prosthetic burn or wiring damage is repaired with RMC cable coil. [color=#c77dff][bold]Nanopaste[/bold][/color] repairs robotic or prosthetic limb damage, not human wounds.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMCircularSaw"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMSurgicalDrill"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCWelderIndustrial"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCCableCoil"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUNanopaste"/>
</Box>

## Synthetic Patients

Synths are not biological patients. They should not receive normal wounds, fractures, internal bleeding, organ trauma, or biological surgery.

- [bold]Brute chassis damage:[/bold] lit welder.
- [bold]Burn or wiring damage:[/bold] RMC cable coil.
- [bold]Missing synthetic limb:[/bold] attach the matching limb or robotic replacement.
- [bold]Prosthetic surgery:[/bold] still uses surgical examine information when surgery mode is active.

## Rare Surgical Tools

[color=#c77dff][bold]PICT[/bold][/color] is a scalpel that also functions as cautery. [color=#c77dff][bold]Incision management system[/bold][/color] prepares incision access quickly. [color=#c77dff][bold]Nanopaste[/bold][/color] is for prosthetic repair.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMScalpelPICT"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMScalpelManager"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUNanopaste"/>
</Box>

## Ghetto Surgery

Ghetto surgery means using the real improvised equivalents accepted by the surgery tool components. It is still surgery: you need the correct body part, access state, and next step.

The system grades tools as [color=#98d982]ideal[/color], [color=#ffd166]suboptimal or substitute[/color], [color=#ffae66]bad substitute[/color], or [color=#ff7070]awful[/color]. Bad tools can mean longer actions, higher failure chance, pain reactions, and extra trauma.

### Actual Improvised Equivalents

[bold]Cut flesh or open an incision:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] scalpel-family surgical tools.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalents:[/color] knives, shivs, machetes, bayonets, and glass shards carry scalpel behavior.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="KitchenKnife"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Shiv"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="ShardGlass"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMM2132Machete"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCM5Bayonet"/>
</Box>

[bold]Retract an incision:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] retractor.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalents:[/color] crowbars, knives, shivs, and glass shards can retract.
- [color=#ffae66]Ugly fallback:[/color] hemostat and scalpel-family tools may work depending on the step, but follow the examine text.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Crowbar"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="KitchenKnife"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="ShardGlass"/>
</Box>

[bold]Clamp, extract, or hold vessels:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] hemostat.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalents:[/color] wirecutters and forks carry hemostat behavior.
- [color=#ffd166]Cable fallback:[/color] RMC cable coils can act as hemostat-style tools and organ-clamp substitutes.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Wirecutter"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Fork"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCCableCoil"/>
</Box>

[bold]Cauterize or close an incision:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] cautery.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalents:[/color] lit welders, basic lighters, and RMC cable coils carry cautery behavior.
- [color=#ff7070]Do not assume every fancy lighter works:[/color] use the examine text. Some lighter variants do not inherit the surgery cautery behavior.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Welder"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Lighter"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCCableCoil"/>
</Box>

[bold]Open bone access or remove prosthetics:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] circular saw.
- [color=#ffd166]Accepted substitute:[/color] surgical drill.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalents:[/color] pens, metal rods, machetes, and bayonets carry saw or drill behavior.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Pen"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PartRodMetal"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMM2132Machete"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCM5Bayonet"/>
</Box>

[bold]Repair bone or close bone access:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] bone gel, bone setter, bone graft.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalents:[/color] screwdriver carries bone-gel behavior, wrench carries bone-setter behavior, and metal rods carry bone-gel plus saw or drill behavior.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Screwdriver"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Wrench"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="PartRodMetal"/>
</Box>

[bold]Repair vessels, suture wounds, or stop internal bleeding during surgery:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal vessel repair:[/color] Fix-o-vein.
- [color=#98d982]Ideal suturing:[/color] surgical line.
- [color=#ffd166]Substitutes:[/color] surgical line can substitute for Fix-o-vein during surgical internal-bleed repair. Fix-o-vein can substitute for suturing. RMC cable coil is the rough vessel or suture fallback.
- [color=#ff7070]Important:[/color] this does not make surgical line, gauze, trauma kits, or cable coil external internal-bleeding treatments. Open the patient first.

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMUFixOVein"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="CMSurgicalLine"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="RMCCableCoil"/>
</Box>

[bold]Repair organs:[/bold]

- [color=#98d982]Ideal:[/color] trauma kit when the exposed organ repair step asks for organ repair.
- [color=#ffd166]Suboptimal:[/color] organ vessel clamp.
- [color=#ffd166]Improvised equivalent:[/color] RMC cable coils carry organ-clamp behavior.

### Ghetto Failure Checklist

If an improvised tool does nothing, check these before assuming the item is broken:

- The patient is not in surgery mode, or you are targeting the wrong region.
- The incision is not open, bleeders are not clamped, or the incision is not retracted.
- Head or chest surgery still needs bone access.
- Armor or clothing is blocking the body part.
- The stump is not sealed before limb attachment.
- The item is the wrong cable item: use the RMC cable coil, not station wiring stacks.
</Document>
